Fernando Cordeiro

Lisbon Metropolitan Area



fernando cordeiro@live.com



+351 951 041 248



linkedin.com/in/fernandorpcordeiro

Summary

I have 8 years of experience working with Product Management (as well as Data Analytics) in e-commerce and brick'n'mortal retailers.

I currently work at my own product, Pluckd as SaaS employee engagement platform, and Jerónimo Martins (JM), a food retailer leader in Portugal, Poland and Colombia. In JM, I treat the store as my product, where I coordinate experiments and proof of concepts that might help shape the group's strategy. My goal is to make the future of retail marketing more customer-centric, data-based and integrated.

In my past, I have worked with CRM, Product Management, Data Mining, BI, as well as beer brewing. Besides Retail and e-Commerce, I have work experiences in four countries ranging from Telecom, Food & Beverages, Strategic Consulting and Banking.

Experience

Senior Customer Intelligence and Analytics Manager

Jerónimo Martins

Jun 2017 - Present (3 years 6 months +)

Responsible for carrying out the vision of scaling the capabilities of our retail companies (Biedronka, Pingo Doce, Ara, Hebe and Recheio) by moving knowledge and experimentation from silos to a new, more digitally unified, environment.

Enabled and authored insights based on customer behavior monitoring and business analysis to help the companies chart their course during the covid-19 pandemic (04/2020).

Mentored newly created product and CRM teams to build and launch the first fully personalized CRM campaigns for Recheio Cash & Carry (03/2019) - then I industrialized them (05/2019).

Other activities: promotional performance analysis, segmentation with unsupervised learning techniques, forecasts, product recommendation algorithms, and training analysts in Git, SQL and good practices in ML and Python.

Co-Founder and CPO

Pluckd

Jan 2019 - Present (1 year 11 months +)

Pluckd is a enployee engagement SaaS that, currently in beta. I'm currently iterating short product discovery and product delivery cycles in order to reach market-fit.



Founder

Cangoroo

Apr 2016 - Jun 2017 (1 year 3 months)

Coordinated the release of our MVP to the market. This was a Ruby on a Rails app that used Turbolinks for its Android and iOS versions. Though we received a good user response, the grocery delivery market lost its attractiveness as many new players entered it.

Cnova Product Manager

Cnova

Mar 2015 - May 2017 (2 years 3 months)

Spearheading mobile development and facilitating mobile-first culture at Cnova Brazil (Business unit who runs GPA's e-commerce: responsible for the brands Pontofrio.com, Extra.com.br. Casasbahia.com.br as well as Cdiscount and Barateiro, altogether the 2nd largest e-commerce presence in Brazil), I've led a cross-functional agile team composed of two product owners and two remote teams.

Boosted time-to-market SLA fourfold by internalizing and rationalizing mobile site and Android development structure (11/2016).

Increased Android app conversion by 36% with timely delivery of features and boosted download rates with continuous ASO practices (11/2016)

Outpaced the competition when launched one the fastest, most fluid m-commerce experiences in Brazil (80% decrease in loading time; 12/2015).

Instilled Scrum and KPI-oriented culture for continuous improvement in platform stability, performance and product development.

Slashed area's total costs 50% by negotiating fees and introducing governance processes, while ensuring the continuation and enhancements of services. (05/2015).

Led quality assurance (QA) and bug management for Cnova's flagships: Extra.com.br, Pontofrio and Casas Bahia, as well as Barateiro, Cdiscount, Pontofrio Atacado for both mobile sites and apps.

Chova CRM Data Analyst

Cnova

May 2012 - Feb 2015 (2 years 10 months)

First hire of CRM area, performed a broad range of functions as it was formed and matured: structured and validated the data warehouse, delivered many BI analyses and CRM studies, designed customer segments and the area's KPI's as well as creating algorithms through data mining.

Algorithms created: product recommendation, market basket analysis & clustering, churn, customer fallout, and channel attribution models.

Trained junior analysts in Web Analytics, SAS and SAS Miner

Created automated routines and that leveraged the results of Email Marketing, Fraud Detection, B2B partners and Sales.

Designed Cnova's campaign manager for automatic email campaigns.

Lead the deployment of Adobe Audience Manager after picking the project with a month behind schedule and delivered it two weeks ahead of time.

Business Consultant

OThink

Jan 2011 - Apr 2012 (1 year 4 months)

Tackled several projects involving logistic process redesign, business intelligence and call-center revitalization. For further details, please see below.

Human Factors Research Assistant

Beckman Institute - University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Oct 2006 - May 2007 (8 months)

Carried on experiments about visual cognition and decision making. Managed the recruitment of volunteers and performed data analysis.

Education

FGV - Fundação Getulio Vargas

Master in Business Economics, Economics 2011 - 2013

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Scholarship, Industrial Engineering 2006 - 2007

Universidade de São Paulo

B.S., Industrial Engineering 2003 - 2008

Licenses & Certifications

- Gamification Coursera
- Mining Massive Datasets Coursera
- Machine Learning Coursera
- Software Processes and Agile Practices Coursera